There's one in every family.
Lilo & Stitch is a animation, family, comedy film directed by Chris Sanders.
As Stitch, a runaway genetic experiment from a faraway planet, wreaks havoc on the Hawaiian Islands, he becomes the mischievous adopted alien
"puppy" of an independent little girl named Lilo and learns about loyalty, friendship, and ʻohana, the Hawaiian tradition of family.
Lilo (voice), played by Daveigh Chase.
Stitch (voice), played by Chris Sanders.
Nani (voice), played by Tia Carrere.
Jumba (voice), played by David Ogden Stiers.
Pleakley (voice), played by Kevin McDonald.
Cobra Bubbles (voice), played by Ving Rhames.
Lilo & Stitch is a 2002 American animated science fiction comedy-drama film written and directed
by Chris Sanders and Dean DeBlois, based on an original story created by Sanders.
It was produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, and stars Daveigh Chase and Sanders as the voices of the title characters, respectively, with the voices of
Tia Carrere, David Ogden Stiers, Kevin McDonald, Ving Rhames, Jason Scott Lee, Zoe Caldwell, and Kevin Michael Richardson in supporting roles.
It was the second of three Disney animated feature films produced primarily at the Florida
animation studio in Disney-MGM Studios at Walt Disney World near Orlando, Florida.
The film tells the story of two individuals: an orphaned Hawaiian girl named Lilo Pelekai, who is raised by her struggling older sister, Nani, after their
parents' deaths, and the genetically engineered extraterrestrial creature Experiment 626, whom Lilo adopts as her "dog" and renames "Stitch".
Stitch, who was designed to cause chaos and destruction, initially uses
Lilo to avoid recapture by an intergalactic federation.
They develop a close bond through the Hawaiian concept of ʻohana, or extended family, causing Stitch
to reconsider his intended destructive purpose, to keep his newfound family together.
The film is based on an idea by Sanders, who originally conceived Stitch in 1981, and
the film's design and aesthetics are based on his personal art style.
Stitch was initially at the center of a children's book
Sanders had conceptualized, but later abandoned.
A feature-length film starring the character entered development in 1997 when Thomas Schumacher, then the president of Walt Disney Feature Animation, approached Sanders with the objective
of producing "the Dumbo for our generation." The use of watercolor backgrounds hearkened back to early Disney productions such as Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs (1937).
The film and its accompanying soundtrack made extensive use of the music of
Elvis Presley, while Alan Silvestri composed the film's score.
Lilo & Stitch premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Los Angeles on June 16,
2002, and was theatrically released in the United States on June 21.
The film received positive reviews from critics, who praised
its story, humor, charm, and originality.
Produced on an $80 million budget and promoted with a marketing campaign that played up its
oddities, it was a box-office success, grossing over $273 million worldwide.
It was nominated for Best Animated Feature at the 75th
Academy Awards, but lost to Spirited Away.
The film's success made it a highlight of Disney's post-animation renaissance era in the 2000s, spawning a franchise that includes
three direct-to-video film sequels, three television series, and a live-action adaptation that was released in 2025.
The film explores themes of sibling relationship, mutation,
extraterrestrial technology, hawaii, adoption.
The tone is lighthearted.